Finding Aid for Inter-University Consortium for Political and Social Research records, 1962-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Individual Council Chairs' Papers 1988-2002
  - Carole Shammas
    Carole Shammas, (Professor of History, University of Southern California. Council member, 1994-1996; Council Chair: 1996-1998). Carole Shammas' papers contain a larger amount of material on governance documents and information pertaining to personnel matters.
    - Governance 1996-1998 (Box 13)
    - Memo. Of Agreement 1996-1998 (Box 13)
    - Programmatic review 1995-1998 (Box 13)
    - Reappointment of Richard Rockwell 1996 (Box 13)
    - Review of Richard Rockwell 1998-1999 (Box 13)
  - Halliman Winsborough
    Halliman Winsborough, (Professor Emeritus, Department of Sociology, University of Wisconsin-Madison. Acting Director of ICPSR, 2000; Council member, 1996-2002; Council Chair: 1998-2000). Halliman Winsborough served as Acting Director of ICPSR briefly in 2000, during the time period before the permanent appointment of Myron Gutmann in 2001.
    - Correspondence 1998-2000 (Box 13)
    - Memorandum of Agreement 1998 (Box 13)
  - Ann Green
    Ann Green, (Director, Social Science Statistical Laboratory. Council member, 2000-2004; Council Chair: 2002-2004.) The papers of Ann Green, the most recently elected Council chair in this collection, are made up entirely of printed-out email correspondence.
    - Correspondence
      - 2000-2003 (Box 13)
      - 2003-2004 (Box 13)
- Resource Development and Services 1963-1992
  The Resource Development and Services series, (1963-1992, 1.65 linear feet) contains documentation for 1963-1992, with the bulk concentration on the late 1960s, 1970s, and early 1980s. The series is divided into two subseries: Archival Activities (1.25 linear feet) and Data Servicing (0.4 linear feet).
  - Archival Activities
    The Archival Activities subseries covers data processing activities and the maintenance of on-going collections. The files of specific archives document current holdings and requests for data. This subseries also contains policies and procedures for processing the data and creating codebooks. Sample codebooks have been retained from ICPSR's early history.
    - Answered Questionnaires (Box 14)
    - Center for Modern Jewish Studies 1984, 1986 (Box 14)
    - Codebooks
      - Documentation (Box 14)
      - Processing 1965-1972, undated (Box 14)
      - Samples circa 1971-1976 (Box 14)
      - Second Site 1976 (Box 14)
      - Uses 1967, 1970 undated (Box 14)
    - Correspondence and Memoranda 1964-1966, 1974-1977, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Data Archive for the National Center for Health Services Research and Development 1972-1974 (Box 14)
    - Data Processing
      - Basic Glossary of Processing Terms (Box 14)
      - Costs and Steps (Box 14)
      - Data Preparation Manual 1980 (Box 14)
      - Development Activities and Plans 1963-1965 (Box 14)
      - Documentation Efforts 1968, 1984 (Box 14)
      - Necessary Background Materials for Studies (Box 14)
      - Procedures 1965-1984, undated, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Data Processing and Acquisition Priorities 1971-1978, undated (Box 14)
    - Economic Behavior Program Archive 1976-1978 (Box 14)
    - Election Data (Box 14)
    - Formation of a Data Repository 1962 (Box 14)
    - Forms (Box 14)
    - Historical Archive 1963-1975, 11 folders (Box 14)
    - International Data Sets Conference 1992 (Box 14)
    - International Relations Archive
      - 1966 (Box 14)
      - 1967 (Box 14)
      - 1968 (Box 14)
      - 1969, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - 1970 (Box 14)
      - 1971 (Box 15)
      - 1972 (Box 15)
      - 1973-1975 (Box 15)
    - Inventory of Data Resources 1964 undated (Box 15)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 15)
    - Reports and Reviews 1962-1978 (Box 15)
    - Research on the Assassination of President Kennedy 1963 (Box 15)
    - Survey Research Archive
      - 1962-1967, 6 folders (Box 15)
      - 1969-1972, 4 folders (Box 15)
      - 1974-1975, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Data Servicing
    The Data Servicing subseries covers the activities for providing users with data from the archives. This subseries contains descriptions and flow charts of the data servicing process. It also contains statistics about use of data sets. The records of the data library show descriptive practices for providing bibliographic information about machine-readable files. In addition, this subseries includes manuals to help users locate and use data sets.
    - Analysis Deck Samples circa 1972-1974 (Box 15)
    - Availability of Data for Microcomputers 1984 (Box 15)
    - Bibliography for 1957-1977, 1977 (Box 15)
    - Charging Policies for Non-member Data Use 1977 (Box 15)
    - Data Library
      - Bibliographic Documentation and Control (Box 15)
      - Procedures 1976-1978, 1984 undated (Box 15)
    - EDUCOM: Machine Readable Data Files Planning Council 1978 (Box 15)
    - Instructional Subsets of Archived Data 1977 (Box 15)
    - Inventory of Use
      - 1964-1967 (Box 15)
      - 1970-1990, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Servicing Procedures 1964-1984 (Box 15)
    - Statistical Packages (Box 15)
    - Storage 1982-1984 (Box 15)
    - User's Manuals (Box 15)
    - Using SPIRES (Stanford Public Information Retrieval System) to Search the ICPSR Guide 1985 (Box 15)
- Grants and Project Proposals 1963-2002
  The Grants and Project Proposals series, (1963-2003, 3.5 linear feet) covers the period 1963-2002. The series is organized chronologically, with the most recent grant proposals at the end of the series. At the beginning of the series, there is an index of all ICPSR grant proposals, compiled by Erik Austin (Director of Archival Development) in 2005. Austin's list is reasonably complete, however, he notes that his list is lacking in proposals from 2001-2002, and there are several earlier grant proposals that exist in the collection that are also not on his list. The series includes information on both nascent ideas and successfully implemented projects. The grant proposals provide a synthesized narrative about ICPSR's significance to various areas of social science. They also provide documentation about the purposes of various data archives, the history of ICPSR's development, and technological advancements.
  - Grant Proposals Index (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
  - Toward the Development of an Inter-University Data Archive System for Comparative Research 1963 (Box 16)
  - Data Retrieval 1964 (Box 16)
  - Historical Archives (Box 16)
  - Comparative Historical Statistics 1966 (Box 16)
  - Data Processing and Documentation 1968 (Box 16)
  - Proposal to the National Science Foundation for Funds for Supplementary Support of a Specialized Facility for Social Science Research 1968 (Box 16)
  - Proposal to the National Science Foundation for Support of a Special Project in Curricular Development for Training in Data Analysis 1968 (Box 16)
  - Application to the National Science Foundation for Funds for Support of Advanced Science Seminars on Quantitative Political Research 1968 (Box 16)
  - Proposal to the National Science Foundation to Support Data Processing and Documentation for the Historical Archives 1968 (Box 16)
  - Application to the National Science Foundation for Funds for Support of Advanced Science Seminars on Quantitative Political Research 1969 (Box 16)
  - International Data Archive 1969-1970, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Proposal to the Office of Naval Research Group Psychology Program for Renewal of Support for the Development of an International Relations Archive 1970 (Box 16)
  - Application to the National Science Foundation for Funds for Support of a Summer Seminar of the Utilization of Small Group Research in the Study of Small "Natural-State" Political Groups 1970 (Box 16)
  - Proposal to the National Endowment for the Humanities to Support Automation of Statistical Sources of French History 1970 (Box 16)
  - Proposal to the National Science Foundation, Resource Development for Inquiry into Social Crises and Political Change 1970 (Box 16)
  - Survey Research Archive, Expansion of Holdings 1970 (Box 16)
  - Application to the National Science foundation for Funds for Support of Advanced Science Seminars on Quantitative Political Analysis 1970 (Box 16)
  - Survey Research Archive, Resource Development for Inquiry into Social Crises and Political Change 1970 (Box 16)
  - Consumer Attitudes and Inclinations to Buy (1951-1970) 1970 (Box 16)
  - Proposal to National Science Foundation for Support of Documentation to Assist Users of Osiris II:A Social Science Software Package 1971 (Box 16)
  - Development of the Data Resources of the Inter-university Consortium for Political Research, [1971 ?] (Box 16)
  - Joint Proposal to National Science Foundation and National Endowment for the Humanities Renewal of Comparative Data Acquisition for the Inter-university Consortium for Political Research 1972 (Box 16)
  - Data Archive for the National Center for Health Services Research and Development 1973 (Box 16)
  - SETUPS (Supplementary Empirical Teaching Units in Political Science) 1973-1974 (Box 16)
  - Survey Research Archive, Development of Data Resources 1975 (Box 16)
  - Statistique Générale de la France 1969-1970, 1975 (Box 16)
  - Development and Utilization of Urban Information Resources [1975 ?] (Box 16)
  - Criminal Justice Archive and Information Network
    - 1977-1984, 9 folders (Box 16)
    - 1985-1990, 6 folders (Box 16)
  - Data Archiving, Training, and Consultation Services in the Field of Aging 1977-1978, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - National Archive of Computerized Data on Aging
    - 1979-1982, 4 folders (Box 17)
    - 1983 (Box 17)
    - 1985 (Box 17)
    - 1988 (Box 17)
    - 1990-1991, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Work and Career Patterns 1978 (Box 17)
  - Parties, Politics, and Government in the U.S. 1850 to the Present, 1978 (Box 17)
  - Data Archiving, Training and Consultation Services in the Field of Aging 1978 (Box 17)
  - Survey Research Archive, Data Processing Costs and Equipment 1978-1979 (Box 17)
  - Equipment Acquisition 1979 (Box 17)
  - Development of Facilities for Remote, On-line Access to Data Resources 1981 (Box 17)
  - Sharing of Research Data 1979-1982 (Box 17)
  - Family Life and Conditions in the United States (1888-1936)
    - 1982 (Box 17)
    - 1984 (Box 17)
    - 1986 (Box 17)
    - 1989 (Box 17)
  - National Instructional Survey 1982 (Box 17)
  - Adolescent Pregnancy Data Archives 1982 (Box 17)
  - Summer Seminar--Parties, Politics, and Government in the United States (1850-present) 1983 (Box 17)
  - State Legislative Electoral Data 1986 (Box 17)
  - National Archives and Records Administration Machine Readable Records Project 1986 (Box 17)
  - Improvement of Computation and Instrumentation 1987 (Box 17)
  - Robert Wood Johnson Foundation--Provision of Data Preparation and Archiving Services
    - 1988 (Box 17)
    - 1996 (Box 17)
  - National Archive of Criminal Justice Data
    - 1988 (Box 17)
    - 1989 (Box 17)
    - 1992 (Box 17)
    - 1999 (Box 17)
  - Electronic Data and Documentation Management System 1989 (Box 17)
  - Factors in Aging
    - 1989 (Box 17)
    - Continued Development Research Resources 1990 (Box 17)
    - Continued Development of Research Resources 1991 (Box 17)
    - Development Research Resources 1992 (Box 17)
    - Development Research Resources 1993 (Box 17)
    - Development Research Resources 1994 (Box 17)
    - Development Research Resources 1996 (Box 17)
    - Development Research Resources 1997 (Box 17)
  - Completion of Family Life and Conditions in the United States (1888-1936) [Sloan Foundation, 1989] (Box 18)
  - National Archive of Criminal Justice Data 1990 (Box 18)
  - 1990 U.S. Census Data Project, 1991 (Box 18)
  - Training Workshop to Promote Research Use of Empirical Health-Related Data 1991 (Box 18)
  - Research Issues and Data Resources in Gerontology Conference 1991 (Box 18)
  - National Institute of Justice Data Resource Program
    - 1992 (Box 18)
    - 1999 (Box 18)
  - Adding Magnetic Disc Capacity for FTP Services from ICPSR 1994 (Box 18)
  - Prototype Internet Services for the General Social Survey 1994 (Box 18)
  - Grant Proposal Supplement: 1970 Census "Rescue" Study, 1994 (Box 18)
  - Developing the Research and Teaching Capacities of Faculty in Historically Black Colleges and Universities 1995 (Box 18)
  - National Archive and Analytical Center for Alcohol, Drug Abuse, and Mental Health Data 1995 (Box 18)
  - Equipping ICPSR to Provide Direct Client-Server Access to Data and Documentation 1995 (Box 18)
  - National Archive and Analytic Center for Alcohol, Drug Abuse, and Mental Health Data 1995 (Box 18)
  - Equipping ICPSR to Provide Direct Client-Server Access to Data and Documentation 1995 (Box 18)
  - National Consortium for the Study of Violence 1995 (Box 18)
  - Robert Wood Johnson Foundation -- Renewal of Project to Provide Data Preparation and Archiving Services for RWJF 1995 (Box 18)
  - Data Resources Program of the National Institute of Justice 1995 (Box 18)
  - Parallel Processing in the Social Sciences: Developing an Advanced, Low-Cost Application 1996 (Box 18)
  - Race, Overconfinement and Crowding in Juvenile Correctional Facilities 1996 (Box 18)
  - Electronic Preservation of Data Documentation: Complementary SGML and Image Capture 1996 (Box 18)
  - National Partnership for Advanced Computing Infrastructure -- NPACI 1996 (Box 18)
  - Acquire, Archive, Document and Disseminate All Public-use Research Data Sets of the National Center for Education Statistics 1996 (Box 18)
  - Losing Faith in Politics? Trends in Citizen Attitudes and Behavior in Japan and the United States 1997 (Box 18)
  - National Archive and Analytic Center for Alcohol, Drug Abuse, and Mental Health Data. Task Order 6: Full Archival Implementation 1997 (Box 18)
  - Database Subscription and Use of ICPSR Collection [Workshop]--OBSSR (NIH) 1997 (Box 18)
  - An Open, Distributed National Network of Geographically Integrated Current and Historical Statistical Information Services 1998 (Box 18)
  - Knowledge and Distributed Intelligence Initiative 1998 (Box 18)
  - Finding Aids, Bibliographic References, Expert Training, and Integrated Hyperlinks: Enhanced User Support for Web-based Archiving 1999 (Box 18)
  - Integration of Multi-lingual Social Science Data Resources into a Seamless Data Discovery, Analysis, and Dissemination System 1999 (Box 18)
  - Changing Lives of Older Couples (CLOC) 1999 (Box 18)
  - Archiving of Dada Files from National Survey of Midlife Development (1995-1996) 1999 (Box 18)
  - The Health and Medical Care Archive (HCMA): Providing Data Preparation and Archiving Services for Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
    - 1999 (Box 18)
    - 2002 (Box 18)
  - National Archive Center for the National Household Survey on Drug Abuse and Other Data 1999 (Box 19)
  - National Survey of Family Growth 1999, 4 folders (Box 19)
  - Extend the Data Documentation Initiative (DDI)to Facilitate Conversion of DAIS and DDMS to a Web-based Application 2000 (Box 19)
  - Provide and Promote Access to 2000 Census Data, 2001 (Box 19)
  - National Historical Geographic Information System 2001 (Box 19)
  - Transforming Historical Data into Knowledge in the Undergraduate Classroom: A Web-based Approach 2002 (Box 19)
  - Preservation and Access in a Digital World: A Proposal for Keeping Digital Information Current 2002 (Box 19)
- Educational Activities 1967-1991
  The Educational Activities series, (.75 linear feet) includes materials from 1967 to 1991, with a concentration in the 1970s and 1980s. The series mostly contains documentation of the summer workshops on data librarianship and management. The records contain a variety of materials, including correspondence, lecture notes, handouts, course evaluations, workbooks, bibliographies, computer software manuals, and course descriptions. Documentation of the other summer training workshops is sparse.
  - Archive Training Sessions 1978 (Box 20)
  - Data Confrontation Seminar 1969 (Box 20)
  - Data Library and Management Workshop
    - 1976
      - General (Box 20)
      - Evaluations (Box 20)
      - Teaching Materials (Box 20)
    - 1977
      - General (Box 20)
      - Evaluations (Box 20)
      - Teaching Materials, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - 1979
      - General (Box 20)
      - Day 1-Day 5, 5 folders (Box 20)
      - Teaching Materials, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - 1981
      - General (Box 20)
      - Teaching Materials (Box 20)
    - 1983 (Box 20)
    - 1986 (Box 20)
    - 1988 (Box 20)
    - Design and Organization of Data 1974 (Box 20)
  - Guests in Archives and Library Science Classes 1977-1978, 1984 (Box 20)
  - Summer Program in Quantitative Methods 1990-1991 (Box 20)
  - Summer Training Program
    - General 1965-1992 (Box 20)
    - Computer Information (Box 20)
    - Course Offerings 1987 (Box 20)
  - Training the Professional Data Librarian 1976 (Box 20)